Guide to the Leland Stanford Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
- University matters, Series 6
  - Correspondence
    - Incoming
      - F - G, 1885-1889 (Box 6, Folder 16)
        - Fargo, F. F.
        - Fitzsimmons, P.A.
        - Flournoy, Jno. A.
        - Francis, Prof.
        - Galloway, Mason
        - Gommo, Eliza
        - Gore & Company: 7/9/1889 on paving the quadrangle
        - Grant, J. D.
        - Gregg, V. A.
        - Gruber, F.
        - Gunlogsen, Albert H.
      - Hayes, Rutherford B., 1885 (Box 6, Folder 17)
      - Henderson, C. Hanford, 1885 (Box 6, Folder 18)
        - Henderson, C. Hanford
        - Pepper, William
        - Sayre, William L.
        - Frazer, Persifor
        - Beach, A. E.
        - Smith, Edgar F.
      - Hogg, Alexander, 1885-1889 (Box 6, Folder 19)
      - Holley, George W., 1884-1885 (Box 6, Folder 20)
        - Holley to Andrew White: 3/17/1885 on construction of lenses for telescopes
        - Holley to Andrew White: 3/19/1885 would White request Stanford's patronage for his ideas on lense construction
        - Holley, "Suggestions for Improvement in the Manufacture of Glass," August 1884
      - H, 1887-1889 (Box 6, Folder 21)
        - Hackett, Mrs. B. S.
        - Hackness, H. W.
        - Hanks, Henry G.
        - Harris, Thomas
        - Haven, Alfred C.
        - Havrmann, W.
        - Hayes, Leslie
        - Heller, N. B.
        - Henry, L. D.: 5/7/1889 requesting a road be laid from the Palo Alto station south to county road
        - Hilton, Mrs. J.M.
        - Hoitt, Ira G.
        - Howell, Lena L.
        - Huntington Hopkins Company
      - I - J - K, 1885-1889 (Box 6, Folder 22)
        - Ingalls, W. F.
        - Ingham, W. T.
        - Jay, Layton
        - Jennings, C. M.
        - Jeune, H.
        - Johnson, Henry: 11/23/1885 on his method of measuring time
        - Jordan, Alice R.
        - Keating, L. N.
        - Keiser, Millie
        - Kellogg, G. M.: 6/7/1887 explaining his idea of a floating school
        - Klenner, R. F.
        - Klipstein, Dr. V
        - Knight, Henry L.
      - L, 1885-1889 (Box 6, Folder 23)
        - La Page, Gertrude
        - Laishley, R.
        - Lawrence, G. A.
        - Lee, Charles E.
        - Leib, S. F.: 4/17/1889 suggesting Stanford be the University President
        - Lenger, J. Henry: 11/13/1888 on German ideas of education and how to use them here
        - Lester, James
        - Low, Frederick F.
        - Ludlow, B.C.
        - Lutido, S.
      - Mohr, Paul, 1887 (Box 6, Folder 24)
        - Oct. 26: letter and list of his geological collection for sale
      - M, 1885-1889 (Box 6, Folder 25)
        - McDiarmid, Mrs. C.
        - MacDonald, Arthur
        - McLellan, Hattie: 10/27/1888 recommending her father Dr. J. A. McLellan for a position
        - Marsh, Charles
        - Marvin, N. R.
        - Maxwell, Will C.
        - Merriam, C. E.
        - Messinger, M. W.
        - Mihills, Lee K.
        - Mitchell, Mrs. Ada
        - Mitchell, Richard H.
        - Monteverde, F. E.
        - Morris, J. N.
      - Olmsted, Frederick, 1887- 1889 (Box 6, Folder 26)
        - 1887, Feb. 11: typed notes re plan of university (not included); not signed but written in Brookline, MA
        - 1887, April 17: Coolidge and Rutan on their way, would like to begin operations this year, have considered board and lodging question
        - 1889, July 14: streets, shubbery, possible changes
      - Peterson, C. F., 1885- 1889 (Box 6, Folder 27)
      - N - O - P, 1885- 1889 (Box 6, Folder 28)
        - Noble, H. A.
        - Otis, Mrs. N. Whittier
        - Park, Carl H.
        - Patterson, Mrs. D.
        - Pereau, J. L.
        - Pomeroy, John N.:1/24/1885: urges Stanford to includes a department of political science in the university
      - R, 1887-1888 (Box 6, Folder 29)
        - Ramel, Eigel
        - Ransom, Louis:5/24/1887 would like to complete some large paintings to adorn the university
        - Rinehart, Imbrie
        - [F. L. O. Roehrig] 1887, Nov. 5: group letter endorsing F. L. O. Roehrig for the faculty
        - Rosenthal, A.
        - Ross, Albert E.
        - Russell, Minnett
      - Sawyer, Wesley C., 1885- 1887 (Box 6, Folder 30)
        - 1885, Dec. 22: heard of conspiracy to exterminate Chinese in California; would like a position with the university
        - 1886, April 14: thoughts on university library's needs, Sawyer family history being written
        - 1887, June 6: working on his book, planning to come to California
      - Sa-So, 1885- 1889 (Box 6, Folder 31)
        - Sawyer, Lorenzo: 5/27/1886: on letters from W.C. Sawyer
        - Sayles, Mrs. Alice
        - Scott, W. E. D.
        - Shepherd, William E.
        - Shepley, Rutan & Coolidge, 4/12/1889: re excavation and drawings for Encina Hall; 5/15/1889: sketch for architect's office
        - Sherman, Henry D.
        - Sieber, W. A.
        - Siler, Jacah
        - Smith, J. K.: 5/11/1889: using felt under the roof tiles
        - Smyth, O. H.
        - Soule, E.
      - Sp - St, 1885-1889 (Box 6, Folder 32)
        - Spence, John F., asking for help in securing memorial to Bishop Newman at Grant Memorial University, with woodcut of the building, 1889 May 7:
        - Spencer, F. E.
        - Spurr, Charles W.
        - Staeubli, Theo S.
        - Stairley, B. F.
        - Steinwand, Otto
        - Stephens, Eleanor G., would like teaching/administrative position at university, 1889 Apr 25 and May 16
        - Stewart, Alex. P.
        - Stickney, George, Jr.
        - Stockton Free Public Library, citizens writing for material assistance, 1885 May 4:
        - Stoneman, George
      - T - V, 1885-1889 (Box 6, Folder 33)
        - Tells, T. S.
        - Thompson, A.B.
        - Townsend, Fred
        - Tracy, S. M.
        - Tubbs, A. L., (tel) accepts position as U. Trustee, 1885 Nov 11
        - Turney, O. A.
        - Turrill, Charles B., on his idea for an industrial museum in connection with the university, 1889 July 1:
        - Unsworth, A. C.
        - Veghte, Henry
        - Vineyard, Anna Oden
      - W - Z, 1885-1889 (Box 7, Folder 1)
        - Waddington, W. W., endorsing Paul Viollet for teaching position, 1889 Feb 15
        - Walker, Francis A.
        - Walter, Carrie Stevens
        - Warmley, J. C.
        - Warner, J. G.
        - Warren, Col.
        - West, Maud
        - White, Andrew D., his impressions of Stanford University and suggestions (TS copy), 1892 May 26:
        - Williams, A. C. B.
        - Williams, Henry B.
        - Wilson, J. W.
        - Wood, J. M.
        - Woodward, A. B.
        - Woodward, Lottie
        - Worcester, Jas., on geological studies with mention of Mills, Davidson, and Agassiz, 1889 July 25:
        - Wright, G. N.
        - Wright, W. G.
        - Zeus, Carl C., recounts his qualifications as art professor, asks for RR pass for travels along coast to complete his "Great Western Album", 1889 June 3:
      - Fragment, 1889 (Box 7, Folder 2)
        - first page endorsing self for position as physics professor; on letterhead of Philadelphia Manual Training School, March 9, 1889:
      - Original index to incoming correspondence (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Act of the Legislature, Grant of Endowment, Address of L. Stanford to the Board of Trustees, Minutes of First Meeting of Trustees, 1885 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Geological collection listing, offered to University [owner unknown], undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Osgood, Azalia A., poem for Opening Day, 1891 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Speech for Opening Day, 1891 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Stocks and bonds, 1899-1908 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Manzanita Water Company
    - American Cotton Company
  - Clippings, 1884-1916 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Autograph books, 1867-1893; Series 7
  - Autographs of U. S. Senators, 1887-1888 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Autographs of U. S. Senators, 1886-1888 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Autographs, 1867-1893 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Autographs, 1877 (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Memorabilia, 1853-1899; Series 8
  - Banquet in honor of Hon. Leland Stanford and Republican Representatives to Congress elect - invitation and program, 1888 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Invitations and calling cards, 1879-1893 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    Includes invitations from President and Mrs. Harrison and Cyrus W. Field; and calling cards of the Stanfords.
  - Menus, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Nevertheless, Afterwards, a Sermon Preached by Rev. A. F. Beard, American Church, Paris, Easter Sunday 1884. Printed for Mr. and Mrs. Leland Standford [sic] at their request (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Railroad passes, 1879-1899 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Pin holder in shape of a fan sent to Leland by Jane Stanford, 1853 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    Accompanying note reads: "This little fan pin holder Mrs. Stanford sent to Mr. Stanford in a letter dated 1853, and again found it when destroying Mr. Stanford's letters in May 1897."
  - Pelton, John C., Life's Sunbeams and Shadows, 1893 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    Includes inscription to Stanfords and holograph poem, 1893.
  - Photograph album of Warm Springs ranch, by Andrews and Lange photographers, circa 1890 (Box 9)
    Includes images of house and gardens, house interiors, family on porch (Josiah W. Stanford?), ranch hands, wine barrels in cellar, vineyards, grape harvesting (interior and exterior scenes).
- Oversize materials, Series 9
  - The Resources of California, San Francisco, 1886-09 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Entire issue; contains story on founding of the University and biographical profile of Leland Stanford.
  - The Centennial Spirit of the Times, San Francisco, 1886-07-04 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    Entire issue; contains story on S. F. residence of Leland Stanford.
  - Zeus, Carl C. - samples of his woodcuts (Box 10, Folder 3)
    Five illustrations plus envelope (see box 6, folder 26).
  - Parry, C. C. - pressed sample of "Stanford Manzanita", 1887 (Box 10, Folder 4)